All right, everyone,
it looks like
it's about that time to get started with
our workshop.
High performance
spatial text, ludic construction
and narrative performance in game engines.
This is going to be run by Patrick Lichty.
And I'll let Patrick introduce himself
and get us started.
I'm mostly here
just to make sure everything goes smooth
here. Yeah.
All right.
Thanks for everybody.
Thanks for everybody for coming.
I'm Patrick, I'm at Winona
State with town and Devin Heckman.
And so a lot of what I do is
I wind up doing a lot of research
in virtual and area and spatial text and
moving forward into XR,
looking at the work of Dean Gregor
and to Haglund.
So let's see here last,
let's see here
I put up a couple of links here.
And so let me kind of
give just a little bit of a.
Preview here.
And what I'm looking at here is I'm, I'm
thinking of the fact
that since I did something along
this line in a, in a non conference
and we had about six hours to work on this
and we've got one hour.
So I had to rethink
this pretty substantially.
So what I'm looking at here is
I'm looking at let's see here.
Let me just.
Let's see here.
Yep I'm going to go in here and.
Kind of get this started.
So what we did
is that we were working on the old
the trope of the old Burma shave.
Signs at the side of the road,
which is actually a Minnesota thing,
which is kind of which I thought was
kind of interesting of the 1920s, 1930s.
So put them out to the side of a road.
And what I thought, wow, wouldn't this be
really cool to be something that's in a,
you know, in a, in a,
in a, in a game environment. So,
I thought that was great.
But then all of a sudden I realized
that I have 160 amount of time that I did.
When? Before.
So what I'm looking at here is this,
I have got a
I've got a, I've got a, I've got a sample
game,
you know, sample sample racing game engine
for Unreal Engine, which is, you know,
the same engine
they used for Fortnite and,
you know, very high performance piece
of piece of stuff, which can also kind of
go out and can go to web.
It can go out to a, a.
Meta quest, etc.
as well as being a console game.
The thing is, is that we
have a computational equity
program here at Winona State
where we've pretty much got small max
and really have to kind of
have to have a decent sized PC
or high end back to run the thing.
So what I am going to do
is because of the time,
what I want to do is that I want to
do a what I call a 3D mesh
kind of net prov, in which
I'll try to assemble them
into the unreal world,
and then make that available in a zip
file out online, which you can play with.
And we can have some later conversations
about,
you know, as a kind of a collaborative
as a collaborative project if you want to.
So what I'm looking at here is that
we'll go from Google Doc,
and I'll kind of show
you a couple of things
here, is that I want to go to the 3D,
3D mesh generator
from AI called mesh,
which I use a great deal.
And then we'll take them over
into another environment called Aqua Make.
So what I'm going to wind up doing
is that, you know,
we'll we'll think about this in a minute,
but let me go over to,
aqua make and I'll just kind of show you
what we did with.
Let's see here.
Okay.
Let's just go over here to make.
And I'll show you what we did for.
The other project.
So this is kind of interesting.
So of course I'm playing a little bit here
with,
with.
Oh bloody hell.
What's that movie.
They live with the no independent
thought here,
but what we wound
up doing is that we wound up.
Making a bunch of Burma shapes in 3D,
which was very fun.
And by the way,
if you want to.
Start taking a look at Aqua,
make a little bit.
That's kind of cool too. So.
But colonizers from afar
who don't recognize Myanmar. And.
So there was a whole bunch
of these things.
But the one thing that I want to try
to get into here
is starting to make 3D objects,
which kind of come from
which kind of put together a serial text.
And this is something that follows
from my ideas on on spatial.
In other words, the idea of taking a net.
Prof.
And then we'll come up with an idea,
then we start making prompts.
And what I want to do is I want to kind of
go over here and show you meshi.
It's a.
And let's see here
right now I've this is one piece
that I've made for.
Made for our world.
And it is the.
It is a hello Kitty shaped
jumbotron for the end of the
for the Apocalypse Apocalypse road.
So that's kind of the deal there. So,
also show you what
our world looks like at the moment.
So I've got a guest in here,
and what we can wind up doing is
we can wind up,
you know, bringing in objects
and putting them in the space.
And what I want to do is I want then
to take, take the objects that we create
and then put them into an unreal project,
which is on my
Alienware,
and then I distribute it a bit later.
So as I said,
we're about eight minutes in.
So what I have here is that I'll go
and I'll
copy the link
and put it out here to the chat.
And. Right.
And then I'll put this out here. And.
We can play with a few prompts
and see what they come up with,
you know, maybe about ten, 15 minutes.
But on the other hand.
So what I'd like to ask you
is that you know, what you think is a
what do you think is a good theme
to start out with that
we can start making prompts from.
So, you know, this could be this could be,
you know, the
this could be the racing game
for the end of the apocalypse or,
or let's see here could also do food.
Foods. Always good.
What do you think?
Whether
World Cup.
How about mythology.
So. Or anybody else
have some some other ideas.
We've got ten people here.
Holy cow.
You know.
Mark, you know that.
You know that kind of.
Okay.
You know, you know, that kind of hits
kind of kind of close to home for me.
But that's kind of interesting.
You know what?
Straits of Hormel throughout time.
Okay I think
we have a lot of good ideas
right here and now. So.
A couple of things
you can go to mesh on your own, but
I'm really fast with it.
I think that
I've got ten people.
Why? Don't see if.
Why don't we see if we can?
I'm going
to put a little bit of a constraint of,
you know, having maybe make a a.
Kind of an ordered
kind of set of prompts,
so we can have some sort of a,
you know, a
little bit of a narrative structure.
And then
I think we've got time travel,
Sanrio based mythologies, and the and the
Straits of Hormel. And.
Which, by the way, is
another Minnesota based trope.
Well. And.
I'm going to say let's go for 11.
And actually, since Mark's here,
you know,
you know how to place the meshes,
you know, you just
you just basically download a globe.
So okay.
So I think that we have stuff in place
here.
Let me just show you really quick.
Let's see here.
Okay.
I've gone in here in meshi.
You can pretty much
just set yourself up with a.
And pretty much set yourself up here with,
with, with just a basic free
account with a couple of generations,
using, using
a Google account or something like that.
And or I'll generate them for you
because I've got a pro account.
And so it's you go on to workspace
and it's text to 3D.
And hey, Mark,
you want to get you want to
you want to rip off one of the first
a first prompt.
Can I hear you?
Sorry about that.
Yeah.
Can we, can we get some an ancient
can of spam
if we're doing Straits of Hormel.
Okay, let's see here.
Can we go further than an ancient
can of spam?
Yeah.
We need a of.
Mesopotamian spam with.
Yeah.
Spam from.
On a ziggurat plate.
Perfect. Too.
Good. Yeah. Maybe with some
we'll mix and match culture.
Some hieroglyphics on there. Maybe.
Well, let's see here.
Okay, let's see what happens. And.
Let's let's do this.
And it'll take a couple minutes.
There we go.
Let's see here.
All right, so
while that's generating,
I kind of want to give you a little bit
of a.
A little bit of introduction to make.
It's basically just kind of a 3D
environment assembly, assembly tool
made by Ukrainian guy living in.
Montreal.
And it's been really good for me
in my classes.
So basically what happens is that
it's basically for putting 3D, 3D
models in general spaces.
It has the ability to
do general moves.
If you're familiar with 3D game
engines at all,
this has the general widget.
This this has the three axis of rotation.
And this also has the.
Scale tool.
And you can kind of bring these around.
And what I have is I have a
just a general landscape.
Where we can drop these things in,
what I have over
and over on my PC
is something a little bit
more like this,
except without the, without the buildings.
So and this is what I want to wind up
dropping these into, as I said,
a little bit more time than we had,
you know, today,
because I want to kind of
get into the get into the net
and building up, building up meshes
and kind of working through there.
So let's see
how this has been coming up.
So let's see here.
Okay.
Oh that's
kind of nice and strange isn't it.
Okay.
Then what we can do is that we can.
Generate a texture for it and.
That's kind of weird.
Let's see here.
Okay.
Yep. This and generate the
texture for it.
Take about a minute.
So what I'll wind up doing
is I'll go over here to the.
Workplace and.
Grab this
put into our net. And.
While we're waiting for that particular
particular piece to come up,
does somebody want to come up
with a second one?
I've got the link
over in the over in the chat
if anybody wants to try a second one.
So as I said,
right at the moment we're at about
we're at about 49,
which means that I think
we're going to be doing
just fine getting the assets in place.
Or maybe
what we can wind up doing is
we could wind up.
Seeing what happens
with. And.
Okay.
Let's see here.
I'll bring this in just for a moment.
And then let's just
bring this in as a GLB.
Okay.
Can of.
Spam with hieroglyphics.
So let's just come in
here. And.
Bring in the can.
Say that's okay.
And there is that.
Strange beast that it is.
And I'll just come on back over here
to my high
speed literature.
And. Kitty
and I'll just bring in a.
New 3D model.
And. Actually,
I think I've got that there.
Okay,
that's really small.
let's
make it big. And.
Then.
Move it around.
Okay.
Oh, that's a really strange
piece of piece of work.
Okay.
Zoom back.
Bring it around.
And maybe
put it on the other side of the road.
And I'll just turn the hill
kitty around. And.
We got the download
done. And.
Okay.
Get that done.
So. Okay.
Is there anything else over in
the other side?
Okay.
Somebody else have a
another artifact that we can put in place.
So the idea here
is that the kind of like other projects
like, like Mark has done, Mark and Rob did
like the,
Let's Mark, what was the secret project
that you and Mark did the,
the grant exhibition of prompts?
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
So in other words,
this is sort of in that vein, except
basically taking taking these prompts
and going forward,
you know, in this kind of
post-apocalyptic scene and then, you know,
trying to create some sort of,
some sort of narrative, you know, in space
that we're going to take in to take
into the game engine
and race by therefore creating,
you know, sort of like, you know,
Strickland or Hayles is kind of read.
Yeah, if you get what I mean.
So, Somebody else
have an idea for a prompt? Oh.
All right.
That's awesome.
Okay.
And as we keep going.
Let's just make some more.
All right.
And we're at 78% on the.
Now. And
and as you can see, you know,
this is kind of like why I'm working
in the way that I am, as in the
in the one hour constraint. So.
Oh that's really good.
Chrome as a statue of Gilgamesh
with my melody is encoded
during their initial battle,
I'm aiming for a Greco-Roman style statue.
The emphasis should be
on the Sanrio similarities.
Very cool.
Oh, look at how that textured.
That's kind of neat.
Okay,
I'll bring this GLB down.
And then then let's just take that it
and then let's texture this.
Oh look at that.
That's great.
That's really strange.
So let's bring.
The other piece in.
Let's kind of take this one out.
Let's bring the other one in.
And when you get the unreal
when you get the unreal file
or I might throw it
on, I might throw it on the web.
It takes a bit of space, but
Hopefully you kind of get an idea of what
I'm getting at here with this idea of.
Okay,
cool. Yes.
Okay.
Super.
Yeah.
It's only about 1 or 2.
So as I said, I'm happy to generate
as many as as we want to do from my pro
plan.
As I kind of said,
what I'm aiming at here is kind of
what I say, kind of a proof of concept
rather than a end of rather
than a finished product.
Let's see here. New
model. Yep.
Let's bring this out here.
Spawn it.
Really small.
There we go. And.
That be kind of careful
because our our.
Advertising
program
partnered up with Hormel last year.
So like this is kind of strange.
Okay. And.
Bring it.
Glenn, what did you make?
I was the one that suggested
the Sanrio Gilgamesh.
I still have my tab pulled up here,
so I can post some screenshots
of what I ended up with.
Or you know what? How big? How? Let's see.
Let's take a look real quick
and see how big the downloads are.
Yeah, they're a bit
they're a bit big to just.
Put over to me.
Yeah, that'd be that'd be great.
Yeah.
The main issue and John pointed out
in chat that they're very careful
about allowing you to use generated models
without paying.
Sure, sure.
Which is the reason why I was, you know,
saying that we could do a lot
of the things through the,
you know, through
the I could just generate from mine.
So I actually have a question about that.
You say you use this in your class? I do.
How are students about generating models
and paying for a subscription to do that?
Well, what happens is that I,
I have a good relationship with the CEO,
and he gives us free access.
Any recommendations for those of us
who don't have a good relationship
with the CEO
that want to use it in classes, right.
Could you use that relationship
to potentially persuade them to offer
an educational program
to increase usage of his platform
and then allow people to apply to it?
I mean, for,
you know, it's in other words,
we make is pretty much free now.
Meshi,
you know, say, for example, Winona State,
you know, I mean, I have, I have, I have,
I have development funds that,
you know, I could in other words,
maybe put $100 into something like that,
or it could be
it could be a lab fee,
something like that.
That's, you know, those are
those are a couple quick,
quick and dirty
solutions is what I would probably
wind up doing in my own,
You know, in my own
classroom, as I'd probably,
I'd probably dump $100 into it,
you know, out of my,
out of my own development funds, probably,
which is not perfect.
Yeah.
The reason I bring this up is
I actually taught an AI course this past
spring, and students were very opposed
to paying for AI subscriptions
or basically anything
that they had multiple good reasons.
One of which is they couldn't
put their financial aid towards it
like they could textbooks.
Right.
And the other one,
of course, being that they didn't
really understand the value of it.
So it's hard to get that persuasion in
because a lot of them saw the value
after using it.
But for any it was hard to see.
And I think 3D models are very heavily
monetized right now because everybody's
trying to get, you know, game development
industry and everything hooked on it.
And it's pretty expensive though,
of course, of course, of course.
I totally see that.
You know, at,
you know, at this point
and I'm not sure is I don't know
whether Davenport Town or around here
is that
I think you can kind of see where,
in creative digital media,
we are really kind of,
caught between, you know, the practical
and the speculative.
You know, we're we're a practice based
research program, but also we're with,
you know, along with other programs,
you know,
like advertising
and that sort of thing, which are,
you know, very,
very practically oriented. So,
you know, that's that's something
that's something
we really wrestle with, actually.
And so this is where,
you know, I kind of had the solution
that I have either, you know, I'm,
I make a relationship with the, with the,
with the platform
or, you know, I just talk a few,
you know, talk a little bit of my,
of my development
money into getting the thing going.
You know, and I think you can understand
that this is probably much better
than trying to get this cleared with it.
Yeah.
Because here at Winona State,
you know, trying to work this out with
it would be a nightmare.
Let's see here.
Okay.
One thing I'm looking into
and have been looking into
is open source 3D model generation,
which has gotten better and better, but
it still is pretty heavy on the triangles.
But a lot of institutions have shared
GPUs.
Sure.
One thing we have here at Winona State,
we've got a
we got lucky enough to have a.
Nvidia, I think DG blade,
that we're now just starting
to get starting to put things together.
And one of the models
that I'd like to try to get going is,
you know,
one to work from my own 3D models
that I've created myself into creating
a set for,
you know, for generation, for our classes
here at state. And.
So let's see here.
Let's see.
How we have here with.
And K2 and friend.
By the way, do do any of you remember the
Ubisoft
game pod basically Planet of Death.
You know, it had these landscapes
that you would go through and,
and that sort of thing.
And this is really kind of
what my influence was in the beginning
of starting to think about this,
because I used to play it for for hours
on end to salt in the background.
So. Let's see here.
Okay.
Do I have it
okay.
Oh that's great.
Okay.
Fantastic.
Let's bring this in.
So I hope that
I'm, I'm kind of coming across here
with the idea that the, you know, the
that the, the virtual narrative and the
and the, and the texts are embedded
within the objects with.
And then the
thing is, is that by putting them in space
and going through them,
we wind up with the reading experience.
The other thing
I think would be really interesting is to
embed sound as well.
And does anybody,
anybody here have some ideas about how.
You know,
one could also create other modalities in.
Working with the reading experience?
One thing I think of is maybe.
You know, like like scripted actions.
Like having things
kind of like.
You know, become
more solid
as you get near them and go by them.
Same with spatial sound.
Okay.
Here is this.
And by the way, Mark,
I'm going to be at your talk
at Siggraph on Monday out in LA.
Hey great.
I'm so happy
I can't wait and see you there.
Good. So okay.
I wonder
what's going on with here with the.
Oh, here it goes.
Oh, that's a wonderfully strange
piece of equipment. And.
And. There we go.
So let's see here.
Is there anything else?
Back in the chat?
Is there anything else back into.
The prompts?
Okay.
Actually,
I also want to shut down a couple windows
because I think that they're probably
starting to kill some of my performance.
The other thing
I'm also very interested in
is also taking these spaces into headsets.
And we can do that from
Unreal Unity fairly easily.
Unreal and on one hand
can go pretty easily to web, which
it creates a very large file.
You know, about, like, you know,
trying to run something on a browser
that's maybe about half a gig.
And then also.
Then also having to use Android.
Android resources to bring things
over into.
Into the headset. So,
so the other thing that we wound up doing
with this is that we wound up, you know,
making these making these assemblages,
taking these out as globes
and then showing them in augmented
reality as well.
Which was also really,
really interesting and fun. So.
Do you think we can pop out
one more or. See.
Not exactly the speed I was intended,
but these are extremely large artifacts.
And Patrick,
you can put the point
to point hyperlinks in there too, right?
Yep. Absolutely.
So, Let's
see. And.
Let's see here. New.
Annotation.
And of course doing this.
Over in
unreal is a completely different beast.
In other words,
winding up, having to bring in an object,
you know, with the
with the text on it in, in
Aqua make what we can do is
these annotations are basically like hot
links, spatial hot links
that we can put in one place to another,
which and you click on them
and they'll take you
through the sequence.
Let's see here.
And. And.
And bring a new.
Annotation in.
Let's just go over to the
workspace in meshi.
Actually this this is actually kind of
interesting that it.
We can kind of take our prompts etc.
from, from meshi and then put them into
our world.
That creates an interesting.
Spam of the ages.
A mark.
Have you gone to Data Land yet?
I have not gone there yet.
In fact,
I was just considering going there,
today.
But it's a little pricey,
so I know, I mean, it's
it's going to be pricey for me too,
but would you like to consider
going Monday or Sunday or Monday,
I mean, Sunday?
Oh, maybe.
Hey, by the way.
Well, let's let's be in touch
because I'm also doing a book
launch event
that you might be interested in on Sunday.
So anyway, too much more promotion.
No, that's all right. So,
As I said, right at this point,
I think where we're at is.
Let's see. And.
New annotation.
So let's see,
let's go over to the workflow.
And get the prompt from.
Think it's over from the.
Yeah.
Making this pop that in there. And.
So and then
see how that works.
Let's just take a look over here at the.
Chat for the.
Oh sorry about that Glenn.
Yeah you're right.
Okay.
Polygon budget for aqua make is.
Well if you want to consider
this you're
pushing the geometry on the on a browser.
So you want to, you know, keep yourself
if possible.
It it does.
You know, it does simplify things.
So it does have its own compressor.
I'd say try to keep yourself
under a couple million, but it will
it will reduce things a great deal.
Yes. You can put audio in the space.
And then sorry about talk
about this side stuff.
But anyway okay.
And then here is another from Watson.
And then I think that
what we can wind up doing is.
Okay.
This is already has sort of come in.
Let me see.
So let's.
Bring that one in.
But how did you generate this one
I mean what
what prompted you give copilot.
Holy cow.
I was just I was just sort of spamming
like Odyssey food monsters
to to make images.
And then when one looked good,
I would just toss it into
one of these other ones.
And. Fantastic.
So I think today
what we've got is the so exercise
in doing a little bit of
A little bit of
spatial riffing. And.
Let's see here.
And then.
That's fantastic.
That's gloriously horrific I love it.
And for some reason
I reminded the Flying Spaghetti Monster
exactly right. Hey,
marching salad troll.
There
we go. And.
And there we go.
And that's that's pretty perfect for that,
I think.
Have it straddling the road.
Now, the thing that I,
I'm wondering about here is that.
Do you think that it's
interesting to be so explicit
as to have having the prompt text itself
as kind of a kind of a kind of a marker
beside the object?
Or do you think that having the object
as a metaphor in itself,
isn't it interesting in itself?
This was a
like a text, like an image prompt,
and like the
the text prompt was kind of muddy, like
came out of a chat that was just like,
like I said, just kind of just like,
hit it until one looks good.
So, like,
the text prompt would be kind of,
yeah, maybe,
maybe a bit too big of a baseball bat.
Yeah. So anyway.
Well, we're at 25, so this is kind of
this was kind of my idea
going forward from the from the Burma
Shave project that we did
in the unconference, to think
about how we can wind up
using 3D spaces and,
you know, prompts as net
to, you know,
kind of populate 3D spaces and,
and maybe fanciful, fanciful
and maybe provocative ways,
depending
on which way you work with the objects.
Patrick,
you can make the prompts into an epic poem
that gets recited over over the piece
as people trip.
Absolutely.
Absolutely, absolutely.
So that's all right.
So okay.
Well,
I think we're
pretty close to time.
Anybody have any closing remarks?
I think we did
pretty well for the amount of time
that we had.
What I would have.
And by the way, what I'll do is
I'll give you my email and.
Please stay in touch and I will
give you links.
To assets as
I continue to develop them.
So anyway,
thanks so much for hanging out with me.
And these things are very fluid
and very chaotic.
And I think that we came up
with some interesting stuff.
All right.
Thanks everybody.
Thanks, John.
Thanks, Patrick.
Thanks, everybody.
Thanks. This was really fun.